A Finding Aid to the Julia Santos Solomon Papers, 1972-2014, in the Archives of American Art
Archives of American Art
Julia Santos Solomon papers
1972-2014
Archives of American Art
Santos Solomon, Julia, 1956-
AAA.santjuli
Archival Resource Key
2 Linear feet
The papers of Julia Santos Solomon measure 2.0 linear feet and date from 1972 to 2014. The papers document Santos Solomon's career as an artist, educator, and fashion designer through a proposal for "Lola!" television show, proposals for a series of children's books, exhibition announcements and catalogs, photographs of artwork, and other professional activity files; writings consisting of notes, diary pages, and diaries; and sketches, sketchbooks, and other artwork.
Biographical / Historical
Julia Santos Solomon (1956- ) is an educator, painter, sculptor, digital artist, and textile and fashion designer in the Dominican Republic and Woodstock, New York. Santos Solomon was born in the Dominican Republic in 1956, and she emigrated to the United States in 1966 where she eventually went on to study at the Rhode Island School of Design and Brown University. Santos Solomon was a founding member of Altos de Chavon School of Design of Parsons School of Design, through which her vision shaped generations of successful Dominican artists. She currently resides in Woodstock, New York.
Arrangement
The collection is arranged into three series.
Series 1: Professional Activity Files, 1972-2014 (0.7 linear feet; Boxes 1-2)
Series 2: Writings, 1977-2007 (0.3 linear feet; Box 1)
Series 3: Artwork, 1985-2002 (0.9 linear feet; Boxes 1-3, OV 4-7)
Scope and Contents
The papers of Julia Santos Solomon measure 2.0 linear feet and date from 1972 to 2014. The papers document Santos Solomon's career as an artist, educator, and fashion designer through a proposal for "Lola!" television show, proposals for a series of children's books, exhibition announcements and catalogs, photographs of artwork, and other professional activity; writings consisting of notes, diary pages, and diaries; and sketches, sketchbooks, and other artwork.
Professional material consists of correspondence with Alice Dye, wife of Pete Dye, golf course architect; commission files relate to golf course landscape paintings, prints, and textiles; some exhibtion catalogs and announcements; and printed material related to Altos de Chavon School of Design. Also included are proposals for a series of children's books consisting of some correspondence, draft manuscripts, and sketches. Audio visual material consists of a DVD and CD related to the pilot television program 'Lola' (never produced) created by Santos Solomon and Barbara Calamari and loosely based on Santos Solomon's biography, especially as a teenager and young adult. Also included are episode descriptions and notes about the show.
Writings include three diaries recording Santos Solomon's study of art and design, largely in the Dominican Republic and Europe. Also included are pages of diary entries from various years, and some notebooks of notes.
Artwork consists of sketchbooks, sketches, fashion illustrations, an original watercolor, pen, and pencil textile designs.
Conditions Governing Access
This collection is open for research. Access to original papers requires an appointment and is limited to the Archives' Washington, D.C. Research Center. Researchers interested in accessing born-digital records in this collection must use access copies. Contact References Services for more information.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Donated 2015 and 2016 by Julia Santos Solomon.
Related Materials
Also found in the Archives of American Art is an oral history interview with Julia Santos Solomon conducted by Fernanda Espinosa, August 26, 2020; an oral history interview conducted by Fernanda Espinosa, March 9-April 15, 2021.
Drawings; Scrapbooks; Sketchbooks; Video recordings; Art teachers -- Dominican Republic; Art teachers -- New York (State); Fashion designers -- Dominican Republic; Fashion designers -- New York (State); Painters -- Dominican Republic; Painters -- New York (State) -- Woodstock; Textile designers -- Dominican Republic; Textile designers -- New York (State); Latino and Latin American artists; Women artists; Diaries; Calamari, Barbara; Dye, Alice; Dye, Pete; Parsons School of Design -- Faculty
- Professional Activity Files, 1972-2014; Series 1; Archival Resource Key; 0.7 Linear feet Boxes1-2
  Scope and Contents
  Professional material consists of correspondence with Alice Dye, wife of Pete Dye, golf course architect; commission files relate to golf course landscape paintings, prints, and textiles; some exhibtion catalogs and announcements; and printed material related to Altos de Chavon School of Design. Also included are proposals for a series of children's books consisting of some correspondence, draft manuscripts, and sketches. Audio visual material consists of a DVD and CD related to the pilot television program 'Lola' (never produced) created by Santos Solomon and Barbara Calamari and loosely based on Santos Solomon's biography, especially as a teenager and young adult. Also included are episode descriptions and notes about the show.
  - Correspondence, 1983-2014; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - "Lola!" Proposed Television Show, 1972-2009; Archival Resource Key; 1 Electronic discs (DVD); 1 Electronic discs (CD) (Box 1, Folder 2-5)
    CD is labeled "Lola."
    DVD is labeled, "Lola! 1. "No Aguanto Mas" by Celia Cruz & Johnny Pacheco 2. "Teatro" by La Lupe"
  - "The Dream of Paolo and Paloma" Children's Book, 1986-1993; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 6-7)
    Contains draft manuscripts for some of the stories and sketches of characters and scenes.
  - "Senora La La the Singing Whale" Children's Story, 1987; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 8)
    Includes draft manuscripts and sketches of characters.
  - Casa de Campo Golf Prints, 1997-2008; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 9-11)
    Related Materials
    Includes sketches and photographs of prints.
  - Altos de Chavon School of Design, Material, 1983-1988; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Antonio Lopez, 1976-1987; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Exhibition Announcement and Catalog, 1983, 2001; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Exhibition Catalog, 2004; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Scrapbook, 2001; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Horseback Riding, Commission, circa 2005; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Photographs of Artwork, undated; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Miscellaneous, 1987-2011; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 18)
- Writings, 1977-2007; Series 2; Archival Resource Key; 0.3 Linear feet Box 1
  Writings include three diaries recording Santos Solomon's study of art and design, largely in the Dominican Republic and Europe. Also included are pages of diary entries from various years, and some notebooks of notes.
  - Diary Entries, 1980-1981; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - Diary Entries, 1996; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - Diary Entries, 2001; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - Diaries, 1977, 2000; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - Diary Notebook, 1996-1997; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 23)
  - Notebook, 2007; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 24)
  - Notepad, undated; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 25)
- Artwork, 1985-2002; Series 3; Archival Resource Key; 0.9 Linear feet Boxes 1-3, OV 4-7
  Artwork consists of sketchbooks, sketches, fashion illustrations, an original watercolor, pen, and pencil textile designs.
  - Binder, Sketches, circa 1987; Archival Resource Key (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - "Natasha Serrata" Sketchbook, undated; Archival Resource Key (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - Painted Fabric Samples Print Designs, undated; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Sketches, undated; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Sketches, undated; Archival Resource Key (Oversize 5)
  - Sketchbook, circa 1987; Archival Resource Key (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Sketchbooks, circa 1992; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 26)
  - Sketchbook, 1997; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 27)
  - Sketchbooks, undated; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Sophmore Designs, 2002; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Sophmore Designs, undated; Archival Resource Key (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - Student Sketches, 1985-1986; Archival Resource Key (Oversize 6)
  - Student Sketches, 1986; Archival Resource Key (Oversize 7)
  - Watercolor Sketch, Flowers, undated; Archival Resource Key (Oversize 4)